<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/master/src/out/critical.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/master/src/out/critical.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>
          Treaty on the soul
        </title>
        <author>Guillelmus Hedonensis</author>
        <editor>Michael Stenskjær Christensen</editor>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition n="0.1.0">
          <date when="2018-10-10">October 10, 2018</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority>
          <ref target="http://representationandreality.gu.se">
            Representation and Reality: Historical and Contemporary Perspectives
            on the Aristotelian Tradition
          </ref>
        </authority>
        <availability status="free">
          <p>Published under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-SA 4.0)</ref></p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <listWit>
          <witness xml:id="C" n="cam">Cambridge, Gonville &amp; Gaius, 342/538</witness>
          <witness xml:id="O" n="chr">Oxford, Corpus Christi College 107, ff. 1--149r</witness>
        </listWit>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <variantEncoding method="parallel-segmentation" location="internal"/>
      <schemaRef n="lbp-critical-1.0.0"
                 url="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/master/src/1.0/critical.rng">
      </schemaRef>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>
          Encoding of this text has followed the recommendations of the
          LombardPress 1.0.0 guidelines for a critical edition.
        </p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc status="draft">
      <listChange>
        <change when="2018-10-10" status="draft">
          <p>Created file for the first time.</p>
        </change>
      </listChange>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="en" type="translation">
    <front>
      <div xml:id="starts-on">
        <pb ed="#C" n="134-v" /><cb ed="#C" n="a"/>
        <pb ed="#O" n="92-r" /><cb ed="#O" n="a"/>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <div xml:id="da-3-d3c6">
        <head>
          Distinction three, chapter six: Whether the intellect knows itself and
          how the same thing can be a sign of itself, arguments attacking that
          and further arguments refuting them.
        </head>
        <p xml:id="da-3-d3c6-io7s60">
          From the preceding we see that the intellect, the knower and the thing
          known are the same. Against this somebody ignorant of
          philosophy usually raises objections, which we will present in order
          to be able to refute them. They therefore say, as if it were entirely
          impossible, that it follows from this that one and the same thing will
          be sign and signified in the same respect both before and after by
          itself and such similar things.
        </p>
        <div ana="#rationes-principales" xml:id="da-3-d3c6-xrp5ue">
          <head><supplied ana="#meta-text">Initial objections</supplied></head>
          <p xml:id="da-3-d3c6-jj1y9m">
            <supplied>
              Argument: An instrument cannot affect itself, the intellect is
              analogous to an instrument, hence the intellect cannot affect (and
              hence know) itself.
            </supplied>
          </p>
          <div xml:id="da-3-d3c6-0h3uxq">
            <p xml:id="da-3-d3c6-lcvp0v">
              Further, they want to argue the point by reducing it to a false or
              impossible point in this way: If a part cannot establish a
              knowledge about its whole, then it is so much more impossible for
              the same thing to establish a knowledge of itself. They want to
              prove the antecedent premise by using insoluble terms such as
              <mentioned>what I say is false</mentioned>, for if this statement
              results in a false understanding about me speaking a falsehood
              then, when I say <mentioned>what I say is false</mentioned>, that
              is the same as if I said <mentioned>I say that what I say is
              false</mentioned>, but so far the statement <mentioned>what I say
              is false</mentioned> gives the same meaning as before, hence it is
              the same as if I said <mentioned>I say that I say that what I say
              is false</mentioned>, and so forth in infinity. But it is
              impossible for anything to proceed in infinity, ergo the first is
              impossible, i.e. that the statement establishes a false
              understanding of that to which it belongs, for that from which
              something impossible follows is impossible.
            </p>
            <p xml:id="da-3-d3c6-pcpw02">
              Further, if that were the case, there would be a procedure in
              infinity, but it is not possible to follow infinite procedures in
              thought, ergo it is impossible to understand that which is
              signified by the proposition <mentioned>what I say is
              false</mentioned>, ergo it does not signify anything. This is why
              some say to this statement that <quote>you are saying
              nothing</quote>, and when it is said that <mentioned>what I state
              is false</mentioned>, they say <quote>you are not stating
              anything</quote>, and that is the argument of annulment and the
              reason for that. But whoever thinks of the statement realizes that
              there is some meaning
              to the sounds <mentioned>what I say is false</mentioned>, hence
              the term <mentioned>false</mentioned> does not establish a
              knowledge of that to which it belongs, ergo it is not a sign of
              itself, and so it is for all other things.
            </p>
          </div>
          <p xml:id="da-3-d3c6-l5c348">
            <supplied>
              Argument: There must be a difference between the knower and the
              known in the process of knowing; if the intellect knows itself
              there is no difference between knower and known; hence, the
              intellect cannot know itself.
            </supplied>
          </p>
          <p xml:id="da-3-d3c6-j9y1li">
            <supplied>
              Argument: The process of understanding combines an accidental and
              an essential element in the soul; self-knowledge is an identity
              between knower and known; the differences between the two elements
              makes an identity and hence self-knowledge impossible.
            </supplied>
          </p>
          <p xml:id="da-3-d3c6-kw5pkf">
            <supplied>
              Argument: If the intellect knows itself by being present to
              itself, it would always know itself; the intellect can only know
              one thing at the time; hence, if the intellect knew itself it
              could not know anything else; the intellect cannot therefore know
              itself by itself.
            </supplied>
          </p>
        </div>
        <div ana="#determinatio" xml:id="da-3-d3c6-vd9l98">
          <head><supplied ana="#meta-text">Determination</supplied></head>
          <p xml:id="da-3-d3c6-p27fzh" ana="#structure-head">
            We now prove by arguments and through authority that this is not the
            case, but that the intellect is a sign and judge of itself by itself.
          </p>
          <!-- Arguments for the doctrine -->
          <p xml:id="da-3-d3c6-zo63m7">
            <supplied>
              Doctrinal arguments supporting the idea of essential
              self-knowledge.
            </supplied>
          </p>
          <p xml:id="da-3-d3c6-g0pv59">
            <supplied>
              Arguments based on authorities.
            </supplied>
          </p>
          <p xml:id="da-3-d3c6-de9rjw">
            <supplied>
              Qualifications and closing reflections.
            </supplied>
          </p>
        </div>
        <div xml:id="da-3-d3c6-c2usdy" ana="#ad-rationes">
          <head>
            <supplied ana="#meta-text">On the initial objections</supplied>
          </head>
          <p xml:id="da-3-d3c6-kfwosi" corresp="#da-3-d3c6-jj1y9m">
            <supplied>
              Refutation: The impossibility of self-affection only applies to
              material objects and senses.
            </supplied>
          </p>
          <p xml:id="da-3-d3c6-dcyya3" corresp="#da-3-d3c6-l5c348">
            <supplied>
              Refutation: There is a difference between the knower and known in
              their definition, but not in existence.
            </supplied>
          </p>
          <p xml:id="da-3-d3c6-8ec1aq" corresp="#da-3-d3c6-j9y1li">
            <supplied>
              Refutation: As above, there is a difference between knower and
              known in their definition, but not in existence.
            </supplied>
          </p>
          <p xml:id="da-3-d3c6-zvyzg0" corresp="#da-3-d3c6-kw5pkf">
            <supplied>
              Refutation: Although the intellect is always present to itself it
              need not always know itself, and it can therefore also know other
              things. Self-knowledge implies process of consideration.
            </supplied>
          </p>
          <!-- From this point, the rest of the text on each folio is surrounded
               by a frame with the note "vacat" marking it as a deletion in C.
               This deletion has clearly been made after the copy of O's ancestor,
               as it is all present in O. -->
          <div xml:id="da-3-d3c6-7sclst" corresp="#da-3-d3c6-0h3uxq">
            <p xml:id="da-3-d3c6-elka1r">
              From these discussions it is clear that when I say <mentioned>What
              I say is false</mentioned>, that statement can easily establish a
              false understanding about that which it is a part and about
              something untrue, to which (to make it more clear) it could be
              objected as follows: When I say <mentioned>What I say is
              false</mentioned>, it is either true or false that is say
              something false; if it is true, then that statement does not
              constitute a false understanding about it, but still about other
              things which are false, although I do not say anything else, ergo
              it is false that I say something false, and the previous statement
              is true; if it is false that I say something false, and I say
              this, then I say something false, ergo it is true that I say
              something false, and something false has been said. In this way
              and in many ways counter-arguments can be made.
            </p>
            <p xml:id="da-3-d3c6-rb5p6n">
              Let us say to this that there is nothing in the way of one and the
              same thing to be true and false at the same time, because
              <supplied>the statement</supplied> <mentioned>man is
              white</mentioned> is true with respect to one and false with
              respect to another. But it is impossible for the same thing to be
              true and false in the same way and with respect to the same at the
              same time. For speakable truth is an equal relation between
              composite pieces of understanding and the disposition of signified
              things in a perfect composition or division (with
              <mentioned>perfect composition</mentioned> I mean affirmative
              statements, with <mentioned>perfect division</mentioned> I mean
              negations). But if there is not an equal relation between the
              elements of understanding and the things, we have a falsity. Thus
              truth is some kind of equality, falsity some kind of inequality,
              just as also <name ref="#Augustine">Augustine</name> testifies to.
              But the concept <mentioned>human</mentioned> is common to any
              particular human, regardless of whether it refers to Socrates,
              Plato, or anybody else, it still refers to the same concept. Thus
              when I say <mentioned>Socrates is a human</mentioned> then I could
              have that shared term, <mentioned>human</mentioned>, refer to
              whichever human that I want, and if it refers to Socrates, then
              there is a truth in the composition. For the thing is the same as
              what the concept holds, and thus there is an equality
              between concept and thing. But if it refers to somebody else than
              Socrates, then there is an inequality in that same composition
              between the concept and the thing, for the thing is not the same
              as what the concept holds. Thus one and the same composition of
              concepts can be true and false at the same time, but on account of
              different things.
            </p>
            <p xml:id="da-3-d3c6-n4mizj">
              <name ref="#Aristotle">Aristotle</name> gives evidence to this in
              <title ref="#Arist.Top">Topics</title>, in the book about
              definitions, towards the end where he says:
              <quote>
                If someone has to define something in relation to something
                else, and he does not relate it to that which it is said in
                relation to in the definition, but to something that contains
                more things, then he has given a bad definition. Suppose for
                example that
                somebody said that medicine is the science of all things that
                exist. For if medicine is not a science about anything that
                exists, then it is clear that the statement is completely false,
                but if it is a science of some things, and not of some other
                things, then it is false in some sense and true in another
                sense.
              </quote>
              Similarly, when I say <mentioned>Socrates is a human</mentioned>,
              when Socrates is a certain human and not another, then it is true
              in one sense and in another sense false.
            </p>
            <p xml:id="da-3-d3c6-grczpn">
              And so in the same way we say that this composition, <mentioned>What I say is
              false</mentioned>, is at the same time true and false, but on
              account of different things. For when the statement
              <mentioned>false</mentioned> signifies the common concept of any
              false thing, and nothing else that is false is said by me, it is
              clear that on account of other false things it is false that
              <mentioned>what I say is false</mentioned>. But when that itself
              is false, and the part can establish an understanding of the
              whole, as it has been outlined, then because of that falseness
              that I say, it is true that <mentioned>what I say is
              false</mentioned>. Ergo <mentioned>what I say is false</mentioned>
              is false on account of other false things, but it is true on
              account of that falsehood that I am saying, and thus the same
              composition is true and false.
            </p>
            <p xml:id="da-3-d3c6-lec8fx">
              <supplied>
                Discussion of the liar paradox continues with many further refinements.
              </supplied>
            </p>
          </div>
        </div>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
